Guide to the Eugene O'Neill Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Eugene O'Neill papers
1872-1970
1930-1959
YCAL MSS 123
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
92.6
(185 boxes) + 7 broadside folders, 4 art storage items, cold storage
The Eugene O'Neill Papers document the life of dramatist Eugene O'Neill, especially his life with Carlotta Monterey O'Neill after 1928. Correspondents include O'Neill's lawyers, Harry Weinberger and Winfield E. Aronberg; his agent, the Richard J. Madden Play Company, Inc.; friends and colleagues; and family members, including his daughter, Oona, his sons, Shane and Eugene, Jr., his third wife, Carlotta, and her daughter, Cynthia Chapman Stram. The collection also contains Carlotta's correspondence after O'Neill's death. There is correspondence with her lawyers at Cadwalader, Wickersham & Taft and at Nutter, McClennen & Fish; the Yale Library system regarding her gift of O'Neill's papers; biographers of O'Neill; others concerning her work on the production and publication of O'Neill's plays; and friends and family members. There are also letters from former husband Ralph Barton before she married O'Neill. Writings include notes, outlines and plot summaries, drafts (typescript and holograph), proofs, contracts, programs, and clippings for many of O'Neill's plays. There are some poems and other writings, as well as his work diaries, in which he documented his writing schedule from 1924 to 1943. There are also some works by others about O'Neill's life and writing. The personal papers include address books, membership certificates, awards for O'Neill's writing, Carlotta's diaries from 1928 to 1964, clippings and ephemera about friends and relatives, and financial material, including cancelled checks and checkbooks. The photographs document O'Neill, his family members, friends, colleagues, pets, and places where he lived and visited. Some of the photographs are in albums. There are also photographs of productions of his plays, from 1916 to 1966. The memorabilia includes office materials, writing tools, jewelry, and locks of hair, among other items. Artists represented in the collection include Cyrus Leroy Baldridge, Miguel Covarrubias, Alfred Joseph Frueh, and Robert Edmond Jones. Some of the artworks are portraits of O'Neill; others pertain to his plays; others were given to, or collected by, the O'Neills. The recordings (all after O'Neill's death) include three recordings of O'Neill plays and one tribute to O'Neill.
O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Eugene O'Neill, Carlotta Monterey O'Neill, and the estate of Carlotta Monterey O'Neill, 1942-1970.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 148-150, 153-181, folders 3268-3269 (Broadside), folder 3271 (Art), and folder 3273 (Art): Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Sound recording located in Historical Sound Recordings: Mourning Becomes Electra (Preston Recording Company: New York).
EUGENE O'NEILL (1888-1953) AND CARLOTTA MONTEREY O'NEILL (1888-1970)
1888 Oct 16: O'Neill born in New York City to Mary Ellen Quinlan O'Neill and actor James O'Neill.
1888 Dec 28: Carlotta born Hazel Neilson Tharsing in Oakland, California to Nellie Gotchett Tharsing and Christian Tharsing.
1906: O'Neill attends Princeton University for one year.
1909 Oct 2: O'Neill marries Kathleen Jenkins; O'Neill goes to Honduras on gold prospecting trip; Carlotta Monterey marries John Moffat (they divorce soon after).
1910 Mar: O'Neill returns to New York City.
1910 May 5: Eugene O'Neill, Jr. born.
1912 Jan: O'Neill attempts suicide.
1912 Jul: O'Neill and Jenkins divorce.
1912 Dec: O'Neill enters Gaylord Farm Sanatorium for tuberculosis treatment.
1913 Jun: O'Neill leaves Gaylord Farm.
1914: O'Neill takes George Pierce Baker's English 47 workshop at Harvard University.
1916: O'Neill goes to Provincetown, Mass.; helps organize Provincetown Players; moves to New York City; Carlotta Monterey marries M. C. Chapman in October.
1917: O'Neill moves back to Provincetown in March; moves to New York City in fall; meets Agnes Boulton; Cynthia Chapman is born to Carlotta Monterey and M. C. Chapman (they divorce within one year).
1918: O'Neill moves with Boulton to Provincetown; marries Boulton Apr 12; they move to West Point Pleasant (N.J.) in fall.
1919: They move to Peaked Hill Bar (Provincetown, Mass.) in May; rent house in town in fall.
1919 Oct 30: Shane Rudraighe O'Neill born in Provincetown.
1920 Aug 10: James O'Neill dies.
1922 Feb 28: Mary Ellen Quinlan O'Neill dies.
1922 Apr: Carlotta Monterey plays Mildred Douglas in The Hairy Ape; she meets O'Neill.
1922 fall: O'Neill and family move to Brook Farm (Ridgefield, Conn.).
1922: Carlotta Monterey marries Ralph Barton.
1923 Nov 8: James O'Neill, Jr. dies.
1924 fall: O'Neill and family move to Bermuda; rent cottage in Paget Parish.
1925 May 14: Oona O'Neill born.
1925 Jul: O'Neill and family go to Nantucket (Mass.).
1925 Oct: O'Neill and family go to Brook Farm.
1926 Feb: O'Neill and family go to Bermuda; rent Bellevue in Paget Parish.
1926 Mar: Carlotta Monterey divorces Ralph Barton.
1926 Jun 23: O'Neill receives honorary degree from Yale University.
1926: O'Neill and family go to Belgrade Lakes (Me.) in the summer; visited by Barbara Burton and Eugene O'Neill, Jr.; O'Neill meets Carlotta Monterey again.
1926 Oct: O'Neill goes to New York; sees Carlotta.
1926 Nov: O'Neill goes to Bermuda; Spithead is renovated.
1927 Aug: O'Neill goes to New York for play rehearsals.
1927 Oct: O'Neill goes to Bermuda.
1927 Nov: O'Neill goes to New York.
1928 Feb 10: O'Neill leaves with Carlotta for Europe.
1928 Mar: Rent villa in Guéthary (France).
1928 Oct: Leave for China.
1928 Dec: Leave for Manila.
1929 Jan 1: Carlotta leaves O'Neill in Colombo, Ceylon.
1929 Jan 15: Reunited in Port Said (Egypt).
1929 Jan: Rent villa in Cap-d'Ail (France).
1929 Jun: Rent Château du Plessis (St. Antoine-du-Rocher, Indre et Loire, France).
1929 Jul 2: O'Neill and Boulton divorce.
1929 Jul 22: O'Neill marries Carlotta in Paris.
1929 fall: Buy dalmation, Silverdene Emblem (Blemie).
1930 Oct: Travel in Spain and Morocco.
1930 Nov: Return to Château du Plessis.
1931 Mar: Go to Las Palmas (Canary Islands).
1931 May: Return to New York City.
1931 May 19: Ralph Barton commits suicide.
1931 Jun: Rent Beacon Farm (Northport, N.Y.).
1931 Sep: Rent apartment at 1095 Park Avenue (New York, N.Y.).
1932 Jun: Move to Casa Genotta (Sea Island, Ga.).
1933 Aug: Vacation at Wolf Lake (N.Y.).
1934 Aug-Sep: Vacation at Wolf Lake (N.Y.).
1936 Nov: Move to Seattle; rent house at 4701 West Ruffner Street.
1936 Nov 12: O'Neill wins Nobel Prize for Literature.
1936 Dec: O'Neill hospitalized at Merritt Hospital (Oakland, Calif.); has appendix removed.
1937 Apr: Rent house at 2909 Avalon Avenue, Berkeley (Calif.).
1937 Jun: Rent house in Lafayette (Calif.).
1937 Dec: Move to Tao House (Danville, Calif.).
1940 Dec 17: Blemie dies.
1942 Apr: Oona chosen "Debutante No. 1" by Stork Club (New York, N.Y.).
1943 Jun 16: Oona marries Charlie Chaplin.
1944 Feb: Sell Tao House; move to Huntington Hotel (San Francisco, Calif.).
1945 Oct: Move to Hotel Barclay (New York, N.Y.).
1946 spring: Move to apartment at 35 East 84th Street.
1948 Jan 18: Carlotta leaves O'Neill.
1948 Jan 27: O'Neill breaks left arm.
1948 Mar: They reconcile.
1948 fall: Move to cottage in Marblehead (Mass.).
1950 Sep 25: O'Neill, Jr. commits suicide in Woodstock (N.Y.).
1951 Feb 5: O'Neill and Carlotta quarrel; O'Neill breaks leg; is hospitalized at Salem Hospital.
1951 Feb 6: Carlotta hospitalized as psychiatric patient.
1951 Mar 23: O'Neill signs petition alleging Carlotta is insane and incapable.
1951 Mar 31: O'Neill enters Doctors' Hospital (New York, N.Y.).
1951 Apr 23: O'Neill withdraws petition against Carlotta.
1951 May 17: O'Neill moves with Carlotta to Shelton Hotel, Suite 401 (Boston, Mass.); they sell Marblehead cottage.
1953 Nov 27: O'Neill dies at Shelton Hotel.
1953 Dec 2: O'Neill buried at Forest Hills Cemetery (Boston, Mass.).
1955: Carlotta moves to Lowell Hotel (New York, N.Y.).
1958: Carlotta moves to Carlton House (New York, N.Y.).
1968 Nov: Carlotta enters St. Luke's Hospital (New York, N.Y.).
1969 Mar: Carlotta transferred to DeWitt Nursing Home (New York, N.Y.).
1970 Jul: Carlotta transferred to Valley Nursing Home (Westwood, N.J.).
1970 Nov 18: Carlotta dies at Valley Nursing Home.
1970 Nov 28: Carlotta buried at Forest Hills Cemetery (Boston, Mass.). For further information, see: Bogard, Travis and Jackson R. Bryer, editors. Selected Letters of Eugene O'Neill. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1988. Boulton, Agnes. Part of a Long Story. Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1958. Bowen, Croswell. The Curse of the Misbegotten: A Tale of the House of O'Neill. New York: McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1959. Gelb, Arthur and Barbara Gelb. O'Neill. New York: Harper & Row, 1973. Miller, Jordan Yale. Eugene O'Neill and the American Critic: A Summary and Bibliographical Checklist. Hamden, Conn.: Archon Books, 1974. O'Neill, Eugene. Complete Plays. New York, N.Y.: Library of America, 1988. Sheaffer, Louis. O'Neill: Son and Playwright. Boston: Little, Brown, 1968. Sheaffer, Louis. O'Neill: Son and Artist. Boston: Little, Brown, 1973.
Scope and Contents
The Eugene O'Neill Papers document the life of the dramatist Eugene O'Neill, especially his life with Carlotta Monterey O'Neill after 1928. The collection consists of professional and family correspondence, manuscripts of O'Neill's writings and materials associated with his writings, photographs, artworks, recordings, legal and financial records, medical records, and personal and professional memorabilia. The papers span the years 1872 to 1970, but the bulk of the material is from 1930s to 1950s. The collection is organized into eight series: Eugene O'Neill Correspondence, Carlotta Monterey O'Neill Correspondence, Writings, Personal Papers, Photographs, Memorabilia, Artwork, and Recordings. The collection is housed in 185 boxes.
Series I, Eugene O'Neill Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: General Correspondence, Family Correspondence, and Third Party Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically. Because Carlotta Monterey O'Neill often wrote on O'Neill's behalf, her letters from his lifetime have been interfiled in this series; her letters written after his death are filed in Series II, Carlotta Monterey O'Neill Correspondence.
The first subseries, General Correspondence, mainly contains holograph drafts of O'Neill's outgoing correspondence, but also includes some original letters to O'Neill and Carlotta. The subseries contains a significant number of original letters from O'Neill to his lawyers, Winfield E. Aronberg and Harry Weinberger, and to his literary agent, the Richard J. Madden Play Company, Inc., as well as carbons of their letters to him. These files appear to have been turned over to the O'Neills at some point by each firm. The files also contain the firms' original correspondence with third parties regarding O'Neill and his work. (Correspondence with known parties is located in third party correspondence.) The correspondence with O'Neill's lawyers concerns literary matters, taxes, and his divorce from Agnes Boulton. The correspondence with his literary agent mainly concerns production and publication of his plays. Other notable correspondents represented in this subseries include Barrett Harper Clark, Saxe Commins, Russel Crouse, Theresa Helburn, Lawrence Langner, Kenneth Macgowan, Léon Mirlas, George Jean Nathan, Carl Van Vechten, and Fania Marinoff Van Vechten. There are also three notebooks containing O'Neill's drafts of letters; these have been cross-referenced under the name of each correspondent. Letters from correspondents not listed individually may be found in "letter" general files. Unidentified correspondence is arranged at the end of the subseries.
The second subseries, Family Correspondence, contains original holograph and typescript letters between family members, as well as O'Neill's holograph drafts of letters. The subseries includes correspondence between O'Neill and his cousins, Agnes and Lillian Brennan; his daughter, Oona Chaplin; his third wife, Carlotta Monterey O'Neill; his sons, Eugene O'Neill, Jr. and Shane Rudraighe O'Neill; Carlotta's daughter, Cynthia Chapman Stram; and Carlotta's mother, Nellie Gotchett Tharsing. There is also correspondence between Carlotta and her third husband, Ralph Barton; Eugene O'Neill; and Eugene O'Neill, Jr.
The third subseries, Third Party Correspondence, contains correspondence between third parties and O'Neill's literary agent, the Richard J. Madden Play Company, Inc., and his lawyers, Harry Weinberger and Winfield E. Aronberg (the latter correspondence includes Eugene O'Neill, Jr.; James O'Neill, Jr.; and Kathleen Pitt-Smith). There are also three exchanges between O'Neill's father, James, and third parties regarding his acting.
Series II, Carlotta Monterey O'Neill Correspondence, is organized into two subseries: General Correspondence, and Family Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically. The correspondence in this series occurred after O'Neill's death. (For any correspondence to or from Carlotta that took place during O'Neill's lifetime, see Series I.)
The first subseries, General Correspondence, mainly contains letters to Carlotta, although there are a few holograph drafts and carbons of letters from her. The correspondence mostly concerns her work regarding the publication and production of O'Neill's plays after his death. Correspondents include Karl Ragnar Gierow, Dudley Nichols, José Quintero, Lars Schmidt, Robert Sisk, and Yale University Press. There is also correspondence with O'Neill's biographers, including Arthur and Barbara Gelb, and Louis Sheaffer. There is a significant amount of correspondence with her lawyers at Cadwalader, Wickersham & Taft, and at Nutter, McClennen & Fish; with the literary agency, Richard J. Madden Play Company, Inc.; and with the Yale University library system (the latter regarding Carlotta's gift to Yale of O'Neill's papers). There is some correspondence with friends, including Mai-Mai Sze, Carl Van Vechten, and Fania Marinoff Van Vechten. There are also three notebooks containing Carlotta's drafts of letters (in shorthand); these have been cross-referenced under the name of each correspondent. Letters from correspondents not listed individually may be found in "letter" general files. There is a small amount of unidentified correspondence at the end of the subseries.
The second subseries, Family Correspondence, contains letters from O'Neill's cousins, Agnes C. Brennan and Lillian Brennan; Carlotta's first husband, John Moffat; her daughter, Cynthia Chapman Stram; and her grandson, Gerald Eugene Stram (and his family). The subseries contains a few holograph drafts and carbons of letters from Carlotta.
Series III, Writings, is organized into six subseries: Plays, Poems, Other Writings, Notes, Work Diaries, and Writings of Others. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically. The first subseries, Plays, contains notes, outlines and plot summaries, holograph and typescript drafts, proofs, production and publication contracts, advertisements, programs, brochures, and clippings of reviews. Annotated proofs are located in this series; unannotated proofs and dummies are cataloged separately as printed material. Contracts for single plays are filed in this series; contracts that pertain to more than one play are located in Series IV, in the subseries, Financial and Legal Material. Photographs of productions are filed in Series V, in the subseries, Play Productions. Artwork relating to O'Neill's plays is filed in Series VII, Artwork. Plays represented in this subseries include Ah, Wilderness!, All God's Chillun Got Wings, Anna Christie, Days Without End, Dynamo, The Great God Brown, Hughie, The Iceman Cometh, Lazarus Laughed, Long Day's Journey Into Night, Marco Millions, A Moon for the Misbegotten, Mourning Becomes Electra, and Strange Interlude, among others. There is some material regarding the plagiarism suit brought against O'Neill for Strange Interlude. There are a significant number of notes regarding O'Neill's cycle plays, as well as drafts of More Stately Mansions and A Touch of the Poet.
The second subseries, Poems, contains mostly typescript drafts. Some of the typescripts appear to be original drafts that were annotated and signed by O'Neill; others are drafts of early poems from 1915 to 1917 that were typed by Carlotta on Tao House stationery in the 1940s. There are a few holograph drafts. In Series IV, there are also some poems by O'Neill that were copied by Carlotta into a volume (box 106, folder 1787).
The third subseries, Other Writings, contains drafts of O'Neill's tribute to his dog, the "Last Will and Testament of Silverdene Emblem O'Neill"; a draft of his acceptance speech for the Nobel Prize in 1936; clippings of O'Neill's tribute to George Pierce Baker after Baker's death in 1935; and a draft of his tribute to Maksim Gorky after Gorky's death in 1936. There are transcriptions by Carlotta for Inscriptions: Eugene O'Neill to Carlotta Monterey O'Neill, which was published in 1960 under O'Neill's name.
The fourth subseries, Notes, contains holograph notes on ideas for plays and for other writings. The notes for plays are not associated with specific plays that O'Neill wrote. (Notes on specific plays are filed in the subseries, Plays, under the title of each play). The notes span the years 1918 to 1938; many are undated. The fifth subseries, Work Diaries, contains four diaries in which O'Neill recorded where he was and what he was working on, from 1924 to 1943. He notes in the first diary that the information was copied from other diaries, except for 1925, which was written from memory (the original diary for 1925 is in the Agnes Boulton Collection of Eugene O'Neill, YCAL MSS 122, box 5, folder 171). The sixth subseries, Writings of Others, mainly contains writings about O'Neill's work and life by various authors, including Croswell Bowen, Barrett Harper Clark, Lawrence Langner, Jordan Yale Miller, and George Jean Nathan. There are also works by Eugene O'Neill, Jr., that he inscribed and sent to O'Neill and Carlotta.
Series IV, Personal Papers, is organized into eight subseries: Address Books, Carlotta Monterey O'Neill Diaries and Calendars, Certificates and Awards, Clippings and Ephemera, Financial and Legal Material, Inscriptions and Signatures, Medical Information, and Personal Writings and Notes. The first subseries, Address Books, contains five address and telephone books that are either in Carlotta's hand or are typewritten. One was signed by her in 1936; the others were probably created by her after O'Neill's death. The second subseries, Carlotta Monterey O'Neill Diaries and Calendars, contains Carlotta's diaries, from 1928 to 1964. These diaries appear to be copies that she made in the 1960s from older diaries; the entries concern her and O'Neill's activities.
The third subseries, Certificates and Awards, contains O'Neill's membership pins or certificates received from the American Academy of Arts and Letters, the American Philosophical Society, and the National Institute of Arts and Letters, as well as awards and medals received during his lifetime for his plays, including the Nobel Prize and three Pulitzer Prizes. Awarded posthumously were the Antoinette Perry Award, a plaque from the National Academy of Recording Arts and Sciences, the New York Drama Critics Circle Award, a Pulitzer Prize, and a certificate showing the 1967 O'Neill postage stamp. This subseries also contains O'Neill's honorary doctorate from Yale University (1926), and one medal that Carlotta received in 1962 from Dramatiska teatern.
The fourth subseries, Clippings and Ephemera, contains clippings from newspapers and magazines; brochures; and programs regarding relatives, friends, and associates, including Ralph Barton, Agnes Boulton, Oona Chaplin, James O'Neill, and Shane Rudraighe O'Neill. There is also material concerning O'Neill and Carlotta themselves. The fifth subseries, Financial and Legal Material, contains contracts and royalty information for productions and publications of O'Neill's plays. The contracts in this subseries each pertain to more than one play. (Any contract that pertains to a single play is filed under the name of that play in Series III.) This subseries also contains cancelled checks, checkbooks, documents regarding O'Neill's and Carlotta's marriage and living expenses in France, tax information, copies of O'Neill's and Carlotta's wills, O'Neill's certificate of discharge as a seaman (1911), a copy of O'Neill's parents' marriage certificate and of his mother's birth certificate.
The sixth subseries, Inscriptions and Signatures, contains inscriptions and signatures that were removed from books owned by O'Neill and Carlotta. The inscriptions are to them from various people and from each other. The seventh subseries, Medical Information, contains a medical record kept by O'Neill's nurse, by his doctor, and by Carlotta, from 1951 until his death in November 1953. There are notes by O'Neill listing the dates that he took the drug, tolserol. There is also a copy of his death certificate and of his autopsy report. In addition, there are medical notes regarding Carlotta from 1954 to 1963. The eighth subseries, Personal Writings and Notes, contains O'Neill's autobiographical notes and a diagram that he made of his family relationship; there is also a folder of his signatures that were cut from envelopes and financial documents. There are notes and reminiscences written by Carlotta about O'Neill and other topics. There are a few writings by O'Neill's father, including his version of Monte Cristo.
Series V, Photographs, is organized into nine subseries: Eugene O'Neill, Carlotta Monterey O'Neill, Other Family, Other People, Albums, Animals, Places, Objects, and Play Productions. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically and then chronologically. Some of the photographs are copies and have been so noted. (In these cases, the library does not own the original.) In addition to photographic prints, there are negatives in this collection (though stored separately). In the case of negatives for which there was no corresponding print, the Library had one copy print made; this information is specified after the folder title.
The first subseries, Eugene O'Neill, contains photographs from 1889 to 1948, including images of O'Neill as a baby and as a young child. The second subseries, Carlotta Monterey O'Neill, spans the years from the 1890s to 1960, and includes some photographs from Carlotta's modeling and acting careers. The third subseries, Other Family, contains photographs of family members, including Agnes Boulton; Oona and Charlie Chaplin; Eugene O'Neill, Jr.; O'Neill's parents, James O'Neill and Mary Ellen Quinlan O'Neill; Shane Rudraighe O'Neill; Carlotta's daugher, Cynthia Chapman Stram; Carlotta's grandson, Gerald Eugene Stram; Carlotta's great-grand-daughter, Denise Dayle Stram; and Carlotta's mother, Nellie Gotchett Tharsing. The fourth subseries, Other People, contains photographs of non-family members, including Ingrid Bergman, Ilka Chase, Lillian Gish, George Jean Nathan, Marian Seldes, James Speyer, Carl Van Vechten, Fania Marinoff Van Vechten, and some of the O'Neills' servants at Casa Genotta and at Tao House. There are a few photographs that were probably collected by James O'Neill of Sarah Bernhardt and Edwin Booth.